So what happens when artificial intelligence gets recursive
self-improvement? What does that actually mean? And what does that gonna mean for us
as human beings in the future? How many paths are there,
and when, some of somebody gets that recursive self-improvement,
what's gonna happen then? Good day, everybody.
We're gonna get into this right at this moment.
Again, so many experts, the AI space,
I can read just like other people, I can comprehend just like other people.
Well, maybe not. Yeah, just like everybody. But not too bad.
So here's what I think. I've been crawling down this rabbit hole since 2021.
How'd I start out as a kid? Programming out of magazines.
They called it programming then. I guess it's not the thing now,
it's programming. It's coding. But here we are today in 2026.
We are getting close to the end of August.
And there's a lot of concern, of course.
It seems like the numbers that are relative towards people liking artificial intelligence,
,are not hating it as vehemently. They're relaxing just a little bit.
Human beings, you know, we're wonderful at that. We get used to things.
And we get used to bad things as well as we get used to
good things. If we start to put on weight,
you know, we get used to it. It isn't until we get there to
this critical level, we say, you know, I'm done.
And then even then, when you're done, yeah, a lot of cases you're really
done. Sorry about that. I've battled with that all my life,
and I finally was able to solve it, but it's always right around the
corner. Lurkin', just like artificial intelligence.
So here's what I think. Right now,
the systems are incredible. They're driven by data.
There's lots, lots of data. In fact,
there's so much data in these systems that apparently the right So they're making
up their own data, called synthetic data.
And now they're using that as a training module for these systems.
Now, all of them have all the data,
but then it has to be educated as to what the data really means.
So they sit down with it. In a way,
in a way of talking, and they start to help it identify certain things.
Once it has all the data and it's trained in a certain way,
then, apparently, they kind of release it into the world after a they do
their checks and balances and fail-safes. So,
that's where you see these little model releases that come out.
Some of them are. Some of big. Some of them are a whole brand
new model they talk about. Some of them are just kind of a change
of the current model. Some of them are all brand new.
Some of them, as you've seen, have been taken away from us as human
beings. We were given it for a little while, then it's taken away.
That was a shock to the system, because that would be like them tying
up the banks, or telling you that, well, sorry.
You can't drive anymore. Your driving privilege has been revoked,
and that includes everybody on the planet.
People that are used, and by no fault of their own,
not that they got popped for drunk driving or got in a crash and
left the seat. or have a car that's in horrible shape,
it's just the decision was made to snatch it.
this large-language model out from public ability to use.
Why? Well, because they say it was dangerous.
And this is the something that happens,
is happening more and more. It's being reported more and more.
It's probably been happening maybe. Maybe at the same pace,
but these little stories eke out into the world and maybe there's a sales
component behind it. Maybe there's a gangster component because,
you know, we like those things that are a little dangerous,
you know, the bad boys. All that sort of thing. Maybe that's the reason.
Maybe there's a bigger reason to release this information to a regular folks up-to-date
on the way artificial intelligence is moving forward.
If that's the case, hey, I'm all for it. But if they're doing it
because it's a marketing stunt, advertising stunt,
kind of a positioning stunt, yeah, I,
I think that's kind of that's a little crass.
That's not really proper, but people are going to do what they're going to
do, and human beings are wonderful at executing execution.
So let's move on. We have these large language models.
They're trained. You've probably dealt with them. You know it was.
No more than three, three years and,
uh, nine months ago or so that Chad GPT interviewed the market in November
of 2022, and what was that,
3.5? Once that made its public debut.
Within a few days, there were millions of people that were using the system,
billions. I mean, just, it grew so fast.
It just made everybody's head swim.
So at the very beginning, if you played with it back then,
it was nowhere near it is today. And tomorrow,
it's going to be nowhere where it is today. It'll be even better.
So it's consistently evolving.
Right now, it's evolving because computer programmers,
people really, really smart in the space. They have good ideas,
they say, hey, maybe this will work better, then they go and they strategize,
strategize, and strategize. They make that happen,
they execute it, and lo and behold, in some cases that works,
whatever this change happens to be, in some cases it doesn't.
But they're still trying, because they're trying to elevate the system far past
where it currently is. So currently,
they're very good at different things. Currently,
they're very good hammers as applied to nails in their own right.
One system might be very good at protein folding.
One system might be very good at playing chess.
Another system might at playing Mario Brothers.
You know, one go. One, one, one,
Medical Research, one this, one that.
But they all have their, their points of ability.
The next step,
or what they would like, and maybe it's already here,
because, and I only say that, because we don't know what's on the inside
of the factory that's building these out. We don't know what's on the inside
of the technological company, the IT Anthropic,
which runs Claude, may be a good chance to be a winner.
We have ChatGPC. which is owned by OpenAI,
another good chance, another big, high-level contender.
The other, ones, Microsoft Co-Pilot,
maybe, I mean, you don't know because for a while Gromit,
Rock was not really heard of until Elon Musk bought a company called Cursor.
I think that's a done deal. But do your research.
But with that, and Brock, and all of Elon's ability
with computing. and these massive data centers that he has,
Colossus 1 and 2, and potentially more,
and the future build out. He's coming back in the game.
So, instead of 2, now maybe 3.
And if Google does something, they're building their own fancy type of chip,
maybe 4. And now you have them all running in the same space.
Maybe Microsoft figures something out,
maybe the open source world out of Thank you.
trying to figure something out. And again,
we keep going. But up until this point, that figuring something out.
These are humans in combination with artificial intelligence,
very smart systems, more than the ones that we're seeing on the planet.
So you're $20 a month cloud membership or,
and, or, uh, opening iChat GPT membership.
Yeah, it's, it's, they're using something a whole different,
whole different monkey for that one. We're watching these things being built out.
and all the news that comes out, and people's big distrust,
and then you have the Doomer saying, well, it's going to end us all.
You have the people that are looking forward to the plenty that it brings
in in the very near future. You know? I don't I'm with,
I want to be with the plenty people because it sucks being negative all
the time. So I'm, I'm all willing to buy into that.
But I'm going to be cautious, and I'm probably not going to be the
first one through the door with a brain transplant or some kind of a
nervous neurological implant to let me be,
or level myself up in accordance with the artificial intelligence systems that make
my brain work. a little better, better, or be more plugged in to the
system itself. But maybe a hundred through the door,
a thousand. Or after they get it done a million times,
kind of my way, but who knows.
Maybe at some point. They'll say, this is great,
and we've done 10, and you need to jump on it,
and for you, it'll be free, because we want you to provide your services.
Who knows what will happen, right? We just never know.
So that's where we're these models are, and they're getting better.
And there's a human in the loop, at least,
what it would appear so, but you hear some of that insider talk that
gets eked out via X or via other social media platforms.
Other media channels, other news reports,
and, yeah, some are saying it's a lot more it than it is us.
It's a lot more of the system doing itself,
the system maintaining itself, learning from itself,
making itself. better than it is us. And if that's the case,
what will be even more interesting is when the system
starts doing it to itself all on its own,
making itself better. I'm sorry, that sounded different.
But making itself better all on its own.
That's called recursive self-improvement. And,
apparently, it's not a real thing yet because it can't
continually be. do it. There's breakage.
There's a shortfall. There's choking.
If you have, uh, your own large language. Model you work with this a
lot of a lot of your your day,
you'll find out that you can give it a task and even.
Even if you give it all the ability,
it mostly will stop short of achieving your goal.
done. It depends on even
when it's given full do everything it it's
going to butt up against a wall, there's going to be some glitch,
some gremlin in the machine that causes it to stop.
That's the, that's improvement of an idea, your idea,
maybe an idea it came up with, and the expansion of the of something
that you want to do, your business, or a thought,
or making your life better, whatever it may be.
Making the entire system better. A little bit different,
but those programmers, those people that are watching the system,
have the same confusion come out of it when you would ask a brain
surgeon, hey, why, why did this human do that right now?
You're monitoring their brain, you have their head strapped with the,
uh, the device with the little electrodes and sensing.
every part of the brain. You have the best equipment monitoring everything going on
in the brain at the level that we can. We can see it.
Why did they just decide to eat that cookie?
Why did they just decide to turn on the TV?
Why, why did they say that they want to go buy a loaf of
bread when they actually have one? It,
why is that? And you can't even tell exactly where
it came from and why it was done.
You ask, these people that are in charge of building out these massive
artificial intelligent brains the same question and you
get an eerily similar answer.
They just don't know. And, yeah,
big enough, enough data, enough information,
fast, instead of running at 40 watts or whatever our brain runs,
gigawatts. It's a bunch.
It's a whole different animal. It's artificial.
Artificial kind of carries with it less than the original,
or not as good. Usually the second movie that comes out,
with very few exceptions, is not as good as the first movie that came
out. Artificial kind of leads you to believe,
yeah, this isn't bad. This is better.
Potentially better than all of us in all respects.
Hence, artificial general intelligence.
Better than us in all areas. So now,
if the scientists that are building out the technology don't really,
don't really fathom as to why it's making decisions,
and aren't really in the loop as far as helping the model improve all
the way as they used to be, then what happens next?
So let's say this, ,this little wall is demolished,
that the ability of artificial intelligence,
whether it's, whether Claude figures it out, whether OpenAI figures it out,
or some Chinese company,
or ... anybody else, fill in the blanks,
some kid in their garage in San Francisco figures it out.
Then at that point, what's that next step?
And I've thought about this and I've watched tons of videos on it.
I've. I've talked to some pretty brilliant people about it and I guess at
that point, nobody else would catch that.
Because,
it would be able to make itself better. It's such a speed and velocity
thing. It already baffles us.
It will baffle us more. And it would move so quickly.
It would go from Artificial General Intelligence to something greater
than that. Maybe different degrees. of General Intelligence.
I don't know if, to get to Superintelligence,
there needs to be more. pure embodiment.
Embodiment meaning there's enough robots out in the field to have explore the physical
world. Physical realm, but I think physics, the movement of things,
the reaction of things, the gravity of things.
Maybe it's been baked in and it's good enough.
I don't know if that's necessary. Way above my pay grade.
But what I do think is when these models do get recursive self-improvement,
if it hasn't happened already, and I don't think it has,
because I think the world would, when that happens,
it will change so rapidly,
one day, the world's this way and tomorrow it's different.
It would be as if an alien force landed on the planet.
Now, I'm not saying in a bad way.
It could be a huge win for everybody.
But, of course, you're going to have some unhappy people.
Unhappy people are in every walk of life.
You have people who have so much money they don't know what to do
with it and they're unhappy. I would like a chance at that.
To be unhappy at that level, because being unhappy broke sucks.
Anyway. So, that's the next step.
That recursive self-improvement, I think that's the game-changer.
And I think if, who knows,
whomever gets it, fill in the blank, it's going to move so quickly that
it's going to get where it needs to get. And nobody will catch up
because, and I was doing a talk yesterday in front of a whole bunch
of real estate agents here in Southern California.
And I didn't finish with this. And I thought this was important enough to
do its own standalone video on. Once it gets there,
whomever the human behind the machine,
I would guess. The first order of business would be,
do not. And I repeat,
do not. Allow any other lab on this planet to catch up with
us. That would be the first step.
Because, in their mind, they're only going to want one artificial planet.
Superintelligence. And that could be moments away,
once it understands how to self-improve.
And when a human being doesn't have to take
the eons of time, capture the what might only take minutes to
see if the model is doing the right thing,
moving in a safe direction. Because time will be of the essence,
yeah, and it doesn't matter,
right? Time is of the essence, yeah,
that's funny, that's a shame, but maybe time is of the essence,
and it will equate to this utopia that people discuss.
Overnight. Very quickly. It could take longer.
It could be that recursive self-improvement never happens.
It could be that, With artificial intelligence,
there's a wall that's hit. Something where there is a cap to prevent it.
Intelligence. You just don't get past a certain level.
Uh, a cat named Fermi.
I think this was in Los Alamos,
New Mexico, which is close to where I live,
and I'll finish with this. Fermi.
He is quoted to have been going out to dinner with some other Los
Alamos smart people and kind of joked and quipped at the table,
what if, what if the reason why we have the haven't met any alien
life out of this massive universe that we have with the
almost countless galaxies, at least from what we can understand,
and more planets, and all of them suns.
and the ability, and a lot of it older than we are on this
planet. Why is it that we've never been visited?
And the conclusion was, well,
they developed superpowers. Superintelligence,
or something better than themselves, and just never made it,
because it wiped them out. That's it.
That's the Fermi Paradox. That's why we haven't met anybody,
according to that particular statement.
Now, Javansberg. The Fermi Paradox is,
you know, everything's going to be in a utopia, cost of everything's going to
go down, it's going to be amazing. I don't know who I have more
faith in. I would hope it's the human to do the right thing.
And if this looks like something that's going to destroy us or harm us,
if, if that can even be figured out, then, then stopping was probably the
best case. However,
right now it's a race. Like the race back in the day to build
as many nuclear weapons as you could because there was a balance.
Balancing Act, Russia was building. Who is bigger?
That was the whole thing, it was a kakoff contest.
Who is bigger? And that happened for a long time until everybody signed a
treaty based on mutually assured destruction.
And everybody, Everybody would die if that would happen. Maybe that's the case where
artificial intelligence will end up being.
Maybe. Maybe there'll be a treaty. But right now,
I think greed and power are winning the game.
It feels like it.
But, we'll let you decide.
Do your research. It could be the most amazing thing that's ever happened to
the human race in the world. Or it could be something else.
Right now, we have very little say.
Right now, the politicians, ,are probably working on trying to figure out if this
open-source thing is even good. Because if they stop us,
...then that could really put a kink in all sorts of things.
And maybe that's good. Or maybe it's bad.
The same thing is if they have these open models,
the public-facing models that you pay for.
Stopping those, or pulling them back after they've so
kindly given them to us. That power flux is interesting.
The political game and insights are also interesting.
And the actual alignment of where everybody is and why this is happening in
its, in its own right. particular way,
which very much feels like a Laker playoff that just never ends.
Yeah. Interesting. I'm Conor with Honor.
We'll see you in the next one. Thanks for watching.